<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://passepartoutvpn.app/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://passepartoutvpn.app/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-03T16:07:38+01:00</updated><id>https://passepartoutvpn.app/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your go-to app for VPN and privacy.</title><subtitle>Passepartout is your go-to app for VPN and privacy.</subtitle><author><name>Davide De Rosa</name></author><entry><title type="html">Deploying to the App Store: The cost you didn’t expect</title><link href="https://passepartoutvpn.app/2025/03/deploying-to-the-app-store-the-cost-you-didn-t-expect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deploying to the App Store: The cost you didn’t expect" /><published>2025-03-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://passepartoutvpn.app/2025/03/deploying-to-the-app-store-the-cost-you-didn-t-expect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://passepartoutvpn.app/2025/03/deploying-to-the-app-store-the-cost-you-didn-t-expect/"><![CDATA[<p>Passepartout has had a <a href="https://github.com/passepartoutvpn/passepartout/actions/runs/13551048532">solid and unique CI/CD workflow</a> for years, from Git commits straight to the App Store. For iPhone, iPad, Mac, and Apple TV.</p>

<p>I dare to say, automated releases are hardly (if <em>ever</em>) seen in open-source *OS apps.</p>

<p><a href="https://docs.fastlane.tools/">fastlane</a>, created by <a href="https://krausefx.com/">Felix Krause</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/features/actions">GitHub Actions</a> helped me immensely with the fast turnaround of Passepartout releases. In the era of LLMs, you have no excuses to waste time for not using these incredible tools.</p>

<p>Let me show why CI/CD is one of the most important and underestimated aspects of making indie software, or software in general.</p>

<h3 id="its-just-an-app-right">It’s just an app, right?</h3>

<p>Many people are confident that <em>The Idea</em> is the most valuable aspect of a product.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, if you developed an app for the App Store, at any level of complexity, you know how exhausting the whole process is. There is so much more than “writing the code”, which is nothing trivial to start with.</p>

<h3 id="the-app-store-requirements-will-beat-you">The App Store requirements will beat you</h3>

<p>Choosing the icons. Crafting the screenshots. Writing the metadata. Picking the categories. Localizations. The business model. In-app purchases. Sorting out the legal aspects. The App Review process. And so on.</p>

<p>Wait, have I mentioned the codesigning process? Development, Ad-Hoc, Distribution. Multiple platforms. Debug and Release.</p>

<p>Especially at the beginning, it’s overwhelming and discouraging. We’ve all been there.</p>

<p>The 15-30% cut that Apple takes from your revenue is almost a marginal cost compared to all this.</p>

<h3 id="the-fear-of-change">The fear of change</h3>

<p>Here’s a very subtle side-effect of the above: once your tedious setup finally works, you might <em>refrain from changing</em>.</p>

<p>Some relatable examples:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If I change the UI, I will have to change the screenshots for X languages and Y platforms.</li>
  <li>If I alter some inner logic, I will get a rejection from Apple.</li>
  <li>If I introduce a regression, I will get bad reviews.</li>
  <li>Even if I have a hotfix in time, Apple will push my release back for silly reasons.</li>
</ul>

<p>It goes without saying, this is an atrocious outcome for your product. If you work alone with no one to delegate these annoyances to, you risk falling into the ultimate recipe for failure.</p>

<p><em>Stagnation is the hidden cost of expensive deployment.</em></p>

<h3 id="you-must-learn-to-automate">You MUST learn to automate</h3>

<p>The key to keeping focus on the product is <em>automation</em>. It’s boring at first, but in the long run, it’s your best bet against the inevitable frustration of using App Store Connect.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If you find yourself doing 3+ times the same task, automate it.</li>
  <li>If a task doesn’t need constant interaction, automate it.</li>
  <li>If a task is sensitive to human mistakes, automate it.</li>
</ul>

<p>Observe your routine and you will soon realize how many hours you are wasting on dumb tasks, time you could have spent on useful features for your customers.</p>

<h3 id="continuous-integration-is-underused">Continuous integration is underused!</h3>

<p>After 15 years working with Apple devices, I can still confirm this trend: the vast majority of iOS developers don’t know jack about <em>continuous integration</em>. Which is crazy because fastlane has been around since 2014. GitHub Actions has a shorter history, but there have always been alternatives: Travis-CI, GitLab, Circle-CI, and whatnot.</p>

<p>In the next posts, I’ll show you how I used fastlane and GitHub Actions to automate the release of Passepartout for iOS, macOS, and tvOS at once.</p>

<p>Stay in touch.</p>]]></content><author><name>Davide De Rosa</name></author><category term="development" /><category term="ci/cd" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Passepartout has had a solid and unique CI/CD workflow for years, from Git commits straight to the App Store. For iPhone, iPad, Mac, and Apple TV.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The path to an obscure crash</title><link href="https://passepartoutvpn.app/2025/03/the-path-to-an-obscure-crash/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The path to an obscure crash" /><published>2025-03-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://passepartoutvpn.app/2025/03/the-path-to-an-obscure-crash</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://passepartoutvpn.app/2025/03/the-path-to-an-obscure-crash/"><![CDATA[<p>One month after its first, painful release, Passepartout v3 is close to being stable.</p>

<p>However, a couple of regressions were still haunting me.</p>

<p>Here I want to describe the absurd journey into one of them, that started with a report <a href="https://github.com/passepartoutvpn/passepartout/issues/1204">from GitHub</a>, and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/passepartout/comments/1j0lbqa/not_open_in_sonoma_any_idea/">one from Reddit</a>. Both users were reporting that the Mac app was crashing on launch.</p>

<p>The reports led me to think that the regression was caused by the macOS version, or the CPU architecture, as both users were using an Intel-based machine.</p>

<h3 id="the-xcode-organizer">The Xcode Organizer</h3>

<p>I had several (unhelpful) crashes in the Xcode Organizer confirming the issue:</p>

<p><img src="/s/posts/2025-03-03-01.png" alt="Xcode Organizer" /></p>

<p>Looking further into some crashes, I could spot a few SIGILL (Illegal Hardware Instruction) that reinforced the idea of a platform-related issue. Add to that, one of the threads had intense Core Data + CloudKit activity ongoing. It must be Core Data, I thought, given that Passepartout performs its sync precisely when the app launches.</p>

<p><em>Doubt #1: how can the app launch at all if the arch is unsupported?</em></p>

<p><em>Doubt #2: is the Core Data stack trace relevant? Is it the thread that is actually crashing?</em></p>

<h3 id="never-read-crash-reports-only-once">Never read crash reports only once</h3>

<p>Passepartout is a privacy-oriented app. There is no external framework e.g. Firebase to help with crash resolution, so Xcode is the only technical resource at disposal. Plus the patient support from the affected users.</p>

<p>Eventually, Core Data was a distraction. Every report was crashing on “Thread 0”, i.e. the main thread. There were also crashes from macOS 15 and ARM64. Fewer, but non-zero.</p>

<p>This stack trace shed some light in that the injected AppDelegate could be the culprit. But where? And why?</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Thread 0 Crashed:
0   Passepartout                    0x00000001029bb154 0x102764000 + 2453844
1   Passepartout                    0x00000001029baf6c 0x102764000 + 2453356
2   Passepartout                    0x00000001029bb83c 0x102764000 + 2455612
3   Passepartout                    0x00000001029ba6ac 0x102764000 + 2451116
4   Passepartout                    0x00000001029b66d4 0x102764000 + 2434772
5   Passepartout                    0x000000010276d0d4 0x102764000 + 37076
6   Passepartout                    0x000000010276c868 0x102764000 + 34920
7   libdispatch.dylib               0x000000018ab68658 _dispatch_client_callout + 20 (object.m:576)
8   libdispatch.dylib               0x000000018ab69ea0 _dispatch_once_callout + 32 (once.c:52)
9   Passepartout                    0x000000010276b2ac 0x102764000 + 29356
10  Passepartout                    0x000000010276b2f0 0x102764000 + 29424
11  Passepartout                    0x000000010276b3c0 0x102764000 + 29632
12  SwiftUI                         0x00000001b977a934 FallbackDelegateBox.delegate.getter + 68 (FallbackDelegateBox.swift:36)
13  SwiftUI                         0x00000001b9e8cea8 specialized NSApplicationDelegateAdaptor.wrappedValue.getter + 156 (FallbackDelegates_Mac.swift:93)
...
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="reproducing-the-crash-pt-1">Reproducing the crash (pt. 1)</h3>

<p>Assuming that the AppDelegate was doing something wrong, there was even a much bigger issue: I could not reproduce the crash on my machine. I realized, though, that a friend of mine had an Intel MacBook with macOS 14, so I asked for his help.</p>

<p>He gave me access via AnyDesk to push ad hoc builds to the machine. The latest app version crashed consistently. Off to a good start. At that point, I spent a few hours trying to exclude potentially offending parts from the launch code, sadly to no avail. Consider that any change in the code implied archiving and sending a build via AnyDesk to test it. It was exhausting, and the afternoon led nowhere.</p>

<h3 id="reproducing-the-crash-pt-2">Reproducing the crash (pt. 2)</h3>

<p>I decide to give a shot to virtualization. Most crashes came from macOS 14, and not necessarily from Intel machines, so this could work. These were the steps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Get <a href="https://mac.getutm.app/">UTM</a> to run a VM on Mac. <em>Highly recommended!</em></li>
  <li>Download a restore image for Sonoma (~14GB)</li>
  <li>Regenerate the provisioning profile with the VM UDID</li>
  <li>Send the development build via a shared folder to the VM</li>
</ul>

<p>The app crashes. Hooray!</p>

<h3 id="git-to-the-rescue">Git to the rescue</h3>

<p>Time to locate where the regression was introduced. I rebuilt the app for each commit that sounded relevant, and after 10-20 builds, I found out that the crash was introduced in <a href="https://github.com/passepartoutvpn/passepartout/pull/1200">this pull request</a> about the light/dark mode picker in the app preferences. WTF?!</p>

<p>It turns out, the widely used <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/appkit/nsapp"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSApp</code> singleton</a> is an <strong>implicitly unwrapped optional</strong>:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>@MainActor
var NSApp: NSApplication!
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>and it was therefore used unsafely in this bit of the PR:</p>

<script src="https://emgithub.com/embed-v2.js?target=https%3A%2F%2Fgithub.com%2Fpassepartoutvpn%2Fpassepartout%2Fblob%2Fv3.1.1%2FPackages%2FApp%2FSources%2FUILibrary%2FBusiness%2FAppearanceManager.swift%23L66-73&amp;style=default&amp;type=code&amp;showBorder=on&amp;showLineNumbers=on&amp;showFileMeta=on&amp;showFullPath=on&amp;showCopy=on"></script>

<h3 id="a-race-condition-about-nsapp">A race condition about NSApp</h3>

<p>It’s finally revealed that, very early in a Mac app lifecycle, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSApp</code> may be nil. This was more often the case on macOS 14 than 15, but still a hideous race condition.</p>

<p>Here goes the simplified stack call:</p>

<ul>
  <li>main</li>
  <li>AppDelegate.init</li>
  <li>AppearanceManager.init</li>
  <li>AppearanceManager.systemAppearance.didSet</li>
  <li>AppearanceManager.apply()</li>
  <li>NSApp.appearance = …</li>
</ul>

<p>In the last call, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSApp</code> may be nil and implicitly unwrapped, leading to the crash.</p>

<h3 id="lessons-learned">Lessons learned</h3>

<p>This was one of those bugs that make you question everything—platform differences, architecture quirks, even Core Data conspiracies—before revealing a simple yet insidious root cause: a race condition with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSApp</code>.</p>

<p>The takeaway? Even well-documented singletons aren’t always safe to assume as non-nil. And when debugging obscure crashes, patience and a systematic approach (plus a good VM setup) can make all the difference.</p>

<p>Passepartout v3.1.5 <a href="https://github.com/passepartoutvpn/passepartout/pull/1224">will handle this case properly</a>, ensuring that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NSApp</code> is accessed only when it’s actually available. Hopefully, that’s one less obscure crash lurking in the shadows.</p>

<p>To Apple and Swift: isn’t it about time to discourage/deprecate the use of implicitly unwrapped optionals?</p>]]></content><author><name>Davide De Rosa</name></author><category term="development" /><category term="swift" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One month after its first, painful release, Passepartout v3 is close to being stable.]]></summary></entry></feed>